we needed to find and kill Osama Bin
Laden as quickly as we possibly could I
needed 36
people I needed millions of dollars in
cash I needed guns
ammunition um secure Communications
night vision goggles stun grenade that I
was made a told FBI agent Ali sufan
during an interrogation that MTAR he
actually laughed when he said it he said
you don't know who MTAR is um shanon
airport in the west of there was rumors
that it was used as a staging post for
rendition are you aware of anything I
was arrested and charged with three
counts of Espionage the President says
well now what do we do and everybody
turns and looks at me Life in principle
never ceases to hold the meaning for
each and every person
[Music]
John Kaku thank you so much for joining
me I can't tell you how I am how excited
I am to get an opportunity to speak to
you thank you so much for having me it's
a pleasure my pleasure um okay let's
start from the beginning there's two
things I want to know first of all what
characteristics and attributes that you
have that made you interesting to the
CIA and how were you
recruited I think there were several
things in
retrospect um I had an advanced degree
and I was young I finished graduate
school when I was 24 years old um I
spoke a relatively difficult foreign
language Greek at the time and
um and I I mean it sounds kind of
silly to say it but I had a passion for
for uh Public Service I only considered
jobs in public service and so I thought
oh one of these days I'll end up on
Capitol Hill or in the Foreign Service
and then when I was in Graduate
School uh my
advisor who happened to be a
psychiatrist a very well-known really an
eminent psychiatrist Dr Gerald post um
he's the one that recruited me into the
C CIA he he was a CIA officer under
cover as a uh as a university professor
and uh he recruited me to work in the
office that he had created at the CIA
the office of leadership analysis so
that's how I got in I and I got there at
the age of uh 25 I was young and eager
um I had a degree in Middle Eastern
studies and a master's degree in
legislative affairs but my focus was on
foreign policy and analysis so I was a I
was a good fit for that what what
attributes um were you particularly
exceptionally intelligent were you
mathematical were you analytical like I
when I think about a CIA operative I
think of somebody of exceptional
intelligence you you would have to be I
I'm I'm I guess more intelligent than
the norm I suppose but I remember taking
a a battery of of exams and then being
shown my results and among people in the
CIA I was slightly smarter than the
average CIA officer when I transferred
to
operations I tested much smarter than
the average operations officer but among
analysts I was you know I was just to
the right of the of the
norm so you're in the CIA it's the 19
late 80s 1990s uh you're uh you you have
a meteoric rise yeah it was very quick
um and you were posted you were doing
you were studying Saddam Hussein if I
remember correctly correct reporting in
the administration reporting to
HW yes um you know this was the this was
the nice thing about the office of
leadership analysis which no longer
exists by the way is that this was a
this was a an organization an office
that was mandated by the White House and
that's why it was created because
the president the vice president the
National Security adviser wanted
psychological insights into the people
that they were either dealing with or
opposing as in the case of Saddam
Hussein or let's say the Iranian uh
religious leadership and so um most of
what we wrote went directly to the
principles the the president the vice
president the National Security adviser
the secretaries of state and defense
their deputies and then just a small
handful with people on the National
Security Council it was a very small
audience that we were
targeting um so the gulf Gulf War I
breaks out um and you have to go you had
to go to the White House at one stage
didn't you right what happened you know
on on June 30th 1990 a colleague of mine
wrote a paper saying that he believed
Saddam Hussein was going to invade kuwa
wa he got real push back on this paper
internally because everybody else
believed that Saddam would cross the
border into Kuwait and just take a very
thin very narrow strip of land along the
border that
um that included the southernmost tip of
the Rhea oil field now the Ruma oil
field was 90 something per in Iraq and
just the southern most
bit of it crossed the border into Kuwait
while the kuwaitis were slant Drilling
and they were stealing the oil they
slant drilled underneath the border and
they were essentially stealing Iraqi oil
that was the Iraqis reason for going in
so everybody believed most everybody
believed that Saddam would cross the
border two kilometers take that little
strip and that would be the end of it
and um that's not what my colleague
predicted so what we ended up doing was
just a couple of days before The
Invasion we asked the US defense atache
in Baghdad to drive south to the Border
just drive get in the car and drive and
then drive back to Baghdad and just type
us a cable and tell us what he
saw and what he saw was literally the
entire Iraqi military moving south to
the Border well if you're going to take
two kilometers of
Sandy Wasteland you're not going to send
your entire military to the Border well
that that was clear that he was that
made it clear to us that he was going to
invade all of Kuwait which he did so
what you referred to a moment
ago um that Invasion took place on
August the 2nd
honestly I'm not overstating it but that
was a day that changed my life because I
was 25 years
old I got to the office early and just
as I arrived my boss said don't take off
your jacket we're going to the White
House I had never been to the White
House other than as a tourist and so we
got in a car the driver took us to the
White House we were escorted into the
Oval
Office it was the president the vice
president the National Security adviser
the director of the CIA my boss and me
and that was it
so when the president sits down in his
you know Wing back chair that is famous
on
television um the vice president sat in
the other Wing back my boss and I sat on
a couch and the President says well now
what do we do and everybody turns and
looks at
me and it shook me for a
moment and then I got my bearings and I
said well
here's what we're up against and
everything that I had prepared in those
previous you know four and a half weeks
came
out it was exciting and it was scary but
it made a name for me and I was lucky
too in the respect I was lucky in a
couple of respects I was lucky
because that Invasion took place right
at the point where I felt like I knew
what I was
doing um and
I was just it was blind luck that when I
was hired I was put on the Iraq desk and
when I when I very gently complained at
one point that you know sometimes I
would go a whole day and not a single
cable would come in I would just kind of
sit there all day like well now what do
I
do because nothing ever happened in Iraq
it was the same cabinet since since the
Revolution um our Embassy had like four
people in it the newspapers didn't cover
Iraq NSA the Pentagon didn't really have
any interest in Iraq and so Al even
being formed at this stage no Al-Qaeda
came five years
later Al-Qaeda came in response to the
American response to the invasion of
Kuwait the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait
Al-Qaeda came about because the US sent
so many troops and so many planes to
Saudi Arabia that we essentially
occupied all of Saudi Arabia's military
bases and Osama Bin Laden said that he
wanted to
force the US military out of what he
called the land of the two holy mosques
Mecca and Medina and so he began by
using propaganda saying that female
soldiers were driving in violation of
Saudi law that American soldiers were
having sex in Mecca right in front of
the Holy cabba that women were walking
around the military bases topless or
naked none of this silliness was true uh
but it resonated with Saudi citizens
especially with the very religious ones
and Al-Qaeda was born around 1984 1985
They carried out their first attack that
was called the OPM sang bombing
um OPM sang was a joint military base
between the US Army and the Saudi
National Guard sang Saudi Arabian
National Guard and
um to the best of my recollection it
killed five people none of them were
Americans they were all Third Country
Nationals I think most of them were
Indians that happened to be working at
the base but this shook us because this
this is where I mean I did all of my
grocery shopping at at OPM sang there
were hundreds of Americans there at any
given time um there was a movie theater
and a bowling alley and you know a mess
hall and you could just go spend the day
I we would go do dry cleaning and
grocery shopping and whatever so for
them to have been able to infiltrate it
and set off a number of bombs that
killed you know killed five and wounded
dozens was was shaking to us this was
1994 1995 time period that was in '95
yeah happened to be in Bahrain when it
took place and I I couldn't believe that
it it was a domestic Saudi terrorist
group but that's how it started the
Saudis cracked down hard on it and they
arrested almost two dozen men they all
made identical Confessions on Saudi
television which of course you know told
me that they were that they were coerced
and uh and they were almost immediately
beheaded but uh Bin Laden got away
um fled to Sudan and then later on from
Sudan to Afghanistan and the rest is
history and the history is so so before
911 in July and we'll skip forward here
you notified you were in the CIA you you
came across information that indicated
Al-Qaeda were planning something big
Dick Clark the
former head of the defense defense
secretary in the Clinton Administration
also was trying to get through to the
Bush Administration and he was
indicating something similar a couple of
months later we have 91 and the rest of
course it changed the entire history of
the world the whole world if I was an
American I mean and of course Americans
were Furious and Clinton has spoken
about this and why were the CIA and why
was the Bush Administration not paying
more attention to Al yeah literally
volumes of books have been written on
this and I'm not sure even with those
books if we will ever come to a national
consensus I can tell you what I saw um I
wish I could take credit for saying that
you know that an attack was going to
happen that that came from George
Tennant who was the CIA director at the
time kofer black who was the cia's um
counter terrorism Center Director and
Dick Clark as you mentioned dick dick
had a number of different jobs um in
senior level jobs in government he spent
the entirety of the Clinton
Administration as the senior director
for counterterrorism at the National
Security Council
um he maintained that job very
briefly under George W bush and then was
just pushed out they didn't like him and
it's because dick was a truth tell um
but they saw dick as a
troublemaker the the George W bush
people were not interested in terrorism
in fact condalisa right told George and
dick
that they were overestimating the threat
to the United States that the real
threat to the United States was China
and that we needed to focus on China not
on these Arabs who don't even have a
country right well George and Dick were
the ones who were right and W and
condesa rice were the ones who were
wrong now with that
said this was the biggest intelligence
failure in America americ history and I
don't when I say intelligence I don't
mean just a CIA failure I mean CIA FBI
NSA State
Department defense department everybody
failed the Congressional oversight
committees failed everybody failed so
there's plenty of blame to go around but
in my view the biggest failure was the
failure of the CIA and the FBI to
cooperate with one another on these
cases for example
the CIA knew that the hijackers were in
the United
States they didn't tell the FBI because
they thought they could recruit some of
these hijackers to in to inform on AMA
Bin Laden they didn't know that an
attack was imminent but they knew that
these dangerous guys were in the United
States they didn't tell they know they
were in Flight School John no they
didn't know they were in flight school
and that's a major FBI failure because
the F the
FBI didn't tell the the CIA hey we have
information that these very specific
people these named people are threats to
the United States we can't find them
well the CIA knew where they were were
hide not hiding where they were living
you know San
Diego Florida Florida yeah um we didn't
know they were in flight school but
that's what I mean when I say failure
there was this breakdown in
communication if the two organizations
had had worked together they could have
developed this information like did it
not to anybody at any level even the
clerk at the flight school that these
guys were very specific in that they
told their instructors we want to learn
how to take off and fly but we don't
want to learn how to land well I got my
pilot's license Landing is the hardest
part but it's the most important part so
if somebody were to come up to me and
say I want to learn how to fly but I
don't care about learning how to land
that would be very alerting to me and if
these guys happen to be foreign
Nationals you know with expired visas in
some
cases my first call would be to the
FBI and nobody thought to do that I
remember traveling around the United
States I was all over the place flew in
and out in and back from there was no
security no there was no Homeland
Security there was nothing um there was
a lack of days I mean it has changed
dramatically since that time period of
course um but I I sometimes I wonder are
we doing hindsight bias here looking
back um but then again when you think
about in 1992 the Twin Towers there was
an attack on the Twin Towers as well so
it's not completely
Fantastical
to to wonder you know um well and I'll
tell you another thing
um before 911 this was
1997 um I would was instructed to
support an operation a
uh a domestic operation and I was
instructed to work with the FBI I think
I can say it was in New
York
so two FBI agents when I arrived I just
took the train up to New York two FBI
agents picked me up and they said they
wanted to give me a tour of New York I
said oh no no I I've been to New York a
thousand million times my brother lives
here I said I I don't need a tour they
said now we're going to give you a
special tour and I remember driving up
First Avenue and they pointed at this
unmarked storefront that you would pass
a thousand times and never pay any
attention to it said see that storefront
that's the headquarters for the
Hezbollah cell in New York and they're
planning a giant
attack I said well what the hell are you
guys doing why don't you bust down the
door and grab them he said no no we're
waiting for them to sort of hang
themselves
I never heard of any arrests ever made
in New York of Hezbollah operatives now
if you can identify the actual location
where these guys are meeting and
presumably conspiring to carry out a
terrorist attack don't you think you
might want to do something about it well
you might bug the place even like I mean
at least bug it exactly or recruit
somebody to penetrate
it so so 911 happens where were you on
911 I was in CIA headquarters and that
was that was kind of an important day
for me even before the attacks because
kofer black and I again kofer is the was
the director of the counterterrorism
center kofer and I had an had an
appointment with Ki rice at nine o'clock
to go over something that's very quaint
at this
point so the government printing office
the GPO it's up on Capitol Hill it
prints all government reports the
government printing office was going to
print
imminently a historic a historical
volume called foreign policy of the
United States
1947 to
1969 Greece turkey
Cyprus okay it's no longer in print and
of the thousands of cables Declassified
cables that were included in that book
were the names of
three
Cooperators with the CIA who were still
alive so we were going to go ask coni
rice if she
would order that the three mentions of
those names be
redacted that was it because we didn't
want you know somebody to put two and
two together together and say Hey you
know these guys oh one's still alive
three are still alive whatever they're
all dead now and I mean this you're in
it's it's the 1940s the 1950s so enough
time has passed it doesn't matter
anymore but we had an appointment to ask
her to to just redact these three
names so I walked over to cofer's office
to tell him that the car was waiting to
pick us up at the West
entrance
and 2001 was before we had the ability
to watch TV on our computers that came a
year later so several of us had little
TVs on our desks cofer's secretary had a
little TV so I walked up to the
secretary and I saw she had the news on
and she's watching one of the World
Trade Center Towers burning and I said
what happened to the World Trade Center
and she said a plane flew into it and I
said you know because I'm very smart
right I said you know that happened once
before in the 1930s a bomber flew into
the Empire State Building but it was
very foggy and rainy that day and it's
so clear today how can you not see that
you're flying into the World Trade
Center like what are you stupid and as
soon as the words came out of my mouth
the second plane
hit and neither one of us said anything
and then she turned to me and she said
did you see that or did I imagine it and
I ran back to my office and I said guys
two planes just hit both towers of the
World Trade Center I think we're under
attack and we all ran back up to Ker's
office now there were there were TVs
mounted just below the ceiling um above
his office and to picture his office
it's an enormous room private offices
all around the perimeter for the big
shots and then the rest of us were all
in cubicles so there were maybe 150 of
us in these cubicles
everybody then gathered in front of the
TVs including kofer and all of the other
seniors and we're all just and I I mean
it's you know CNN and BBC and MSNBC and
Russian television and this one and that
one and the French and the Turks and
everybody is covering this
now and we're standing there in silence
finally someone behind me shouts can
somebody please lead and kofer sort of
snap spped out of his stuper and he says
you go to the director's office and and
tell him such and such you go to
security and tell them this you go to
the deputy director for
operations finally a Spoke came a SPO a
special protective officer it's the CIA
police force came into the office and he
says everybody evacuate under the the
director's orders everybody out nobody
budged and then finally someone
said yeah the I I should add in the
interim the Pentagon was hit we knew
that there was still a plane in the air
and then somebody said we should
probably assume that that next plane is
coming for
us and then the spoke came back into the
office and said if you don't evacuate
now everybody will be placed under
arrest and so we all evacuated
well it took me two and a half hours to
get out of the part
lot just to get onto the George
Washington Parkway and then I only got
halfway home and it was it was chaos
like you see maybe in World War
Z so I just abandoned my car on the
highway and I walked the rest of the way
my girlfriend who later became my wife
was um on the top floor at CIA
headquarters she ended up coming to my
place I don't know a half an hour later
we we went to the the roof of the
building and we watched the Pentagon
burn and then we walked around trying to
donate blood but there was a 24-hour
long line and finally I said this is
ridiculous we have to go back to work
and so we walked back to my car and I I
drove across the grassy median and then
went back to CIA headquarters and then I
just stayed there for the next four days
I slept under my desk we we took a bolt
cutter and cut the the chain and lock on
the cafeteria door and we we cooked all
the food and just laid it out on folding
tables in the hallway and I mean there
were hundreds of us maybe a thousand of
us that that just worked 24 hours a day
but you know at this stage okay so it's
all hands on deck there's going to be a
huge amount of attention and focus on
you and what you're doing there be
people at very high levels trying to
figure out okay what do we do now um
and what what what what you did for the
first few weeks the Americans did very
little in terms of organizing it
seems and focusing on say for example
Afghanistan that came later it looks
like it came later yeah we sent the team
into Afghanistan within three or four
days okay yeah uh it was it was a small
team of about a dozen guys uh led by a
legendary CIA officer by the name of of
Gary shron and they parachuted into
Northern Afghanistan they met up with
the Northern Alliance uh and bought
horses uh we also dropped um weapons uh
by helicopter and so they they armed
themselves and then along with the
Northern Alliance began
um
began operations I guess is the best way
to say it against the Taliban but the
idea was we needed to find and kill
Osama Bin Laden as quickly as we
possibly could but he was very well
hidden and the story now is quite well
known
um he he didn't see Gary shon's team as
a real threat not so long as the Taliban
were protecting him it was when the US
Air Force began bombing Afghanistan in
October about three and a half weeks
after
911 that's when Al-Qaeda began to
scatter for the most part the leadership
went to torab Bor we knew that they were
in Tabora and we began bombing it
mercilessly but then the commander of
Central Command made a just a terrible
terrible mistake we had
surrounded almost surrounded the
mountain where Osama Bin Laden Iman zahi
and the rest of the AL Al-Qaeda
leadership were Hol Up we had killed
Muhammad um at who was the the military
commander of al-Qaeda we killed him in a
in a bomb a bombing raid in uh Cabell
but we knew that Bin Laden his family
zaahi his family and all those others at
the top of the food chain were in torab
Bora we had a source who was acting as
as a centcom translator
uh act as the
goet and we told them that we were going
to attack and we were going to kill
everybody unless they gave up and they
said in response they would give up at
dawn if we would allow free passage of
the women and
children and sencom agreed to that hello
everyone uh apologies for the brief
Interruption quick request could
everybody who had has been watching the
content and found the content enjoyable
and perhaps is enjoying this
conversation could you hit the Subscribe
button it makes such a difference to the
channel it really helps when trying to
entice new guests to the platform we're
more likely to receive a favorable
response the higher the numbers are to
everyone that has subscribed so far
thank you so much I appreciate each and
every one of you and now back to the
conversation with John I hope you're
finding it as fascinating to to watch as
I found it to record thank you so
much instead what happened was they used
that night which was about eight hours
of
ceasefire to escape into
Pakistan and so when Dawn
broke nobody came down the mountain
because there was nobody on the mountain
to come down they had all
escaped and and then the hunt began but
the orders were very clear were we were
to we were to capture as many Al-Qaeda
Fighters and Al-Qaeda leaders as we
possibly could uh Bin Laden and
zaii it didn't matter if they were taken
Dead or Alive were you in Pakistan at
this stage or were you I got to I got to
Pakistan the first week of January of uh
2002 and you wanted to get
into yeah want to get into Afghanistan
but boy did I
was one of only 16 Arabic speakers at
the CIA which is just mind-boggling when
you think of it I mean fluent Arabic
speakers there weren't many of us and so
I volunteered
repeatedly to go to Afghanistan now I
had run into a colleague of mine another
legendary figure by the name of Billy W
Billy and I had done an operation
together in uh in the Middle East just
two months
earlier and then Billy
disappeared and so I ran into him in the
hallway in
October and I said hey Billy where you
been and he looked around and he he
whispers to me
Afghanistan and I said really what are
you doing in
Afghanistan and he said I've been
killing people what do you think I've
been doing and it was then that it
dawned on me they didn't need linguists
they didn't need translators they're not
interviewing people they're just killing
them
so I went back to the deputy director of
the counterterrorism center who was a
friend of mine and I saidif you don't
send me to Afghanistan right now I'm G
to resign and I'm G to go straight to
Exxon with my Arabic and I am not going
to look back and so they sent me to
Pakistan as the chief of
counterterrorism operations there and
you know that was very fortuitous
because for the most part operations
against Al-Qaeda had ceased in
Afghanistan we had killed
everybody who we hadn't driven across
the border into Pakistan and then the
first thing that I did when I got to
Pakistan like literally on my first day
I made a recommendation to the chief
there that we pull our officers off the
border and just allow Al-Qaeda to enter
Pakistan because I said look you know
that they're scared and they're going to
make a mistake and as soon as they make
a mistake we have them right they have
nowhere to go they don't speak any of
the languages there they don't speak uru
pashu Cindi Punjabi they speak Arabic
they stick out like a sore Thum they
stick out like a sore Thum you have um
uh for the Pakistani authorities would
be more willing to cooperate than the AF
than the Taliban right oh heavens you
know you hear a lot about the pakistanis
I thoroughly enjoyed working with the
pakistanis I always say that the
Pakistani intelligence service is
essentially two separate organizations
isi is two separate organizations the
half that I worked with were all
educated at um at
Sandhurst they were all that's the
British Military Academy for British
Military Academy correct um many of them
most of them had done military training
courses at bases around the United
States they ALS spoke fluent English and
they were
Fearless the other half were the guys
with the long beards who had created the
Taliban um who were supportive of the
Taliban and of Kashmir separatist groups
terrorist groups and didn't want
anything to do with the United States I
never dealt with any of those people I
dealt with the the counterterrorism
proest people and then when you are when
you are offering them pallets of money
to do what you
want receptive and very receptive so you
come up with a plan to you you can't get
Bin Laden um but you go
after Zu zua right and you get him he
was the very first high value Target
that we that we searched for and he's
number three
in Yeah we believed he was he wasn't in
the end was khed shik Muhammad was he
number two was that the way KH sh
Muhammad was number three was number
three okay see we had never heard of KH
shik muhamed it wasn't until we captured
abua and I'm getting ahead the story but
I think this is important it wasn't
until we captured
abua that we realized several things
number one he was not the number three
in al-Qaeda number two he had never
joined Al-Qaeda he was a bad man he had
founded the al-Qaeda house in pesha
Pakistan called the house of Martyrs he
had founded and managed al-qaeda's two
training camps in kahar uh he was a
logistician for Al-Qaeda he would get
you a a fake passport a ticket home he
would smuggle you into Afghanistan to
make Jihad but he was not the number
three in
al-Qaeda he had nothing to do with the
planning of 911 now on the other hand we
knew and we had known since the 199 90s
that there was this very bad guy named
MTAR we knew that MTAR was a Nar we had
no idea what this person's name was and
the reason we knew about this person was
that in
1996 listen to how crazy this is in
1996 a
housekeeper went into a rented apartment
to do the normal weekly house
cleaning and what she saw was plans laid
out on a table indicating that a
terrorist or a terrorist group intended
to hijack 14 747 jumbo Jets from Manila
Airport and fly them into buildings up
and down the west coast of the United
States it was called the bojinka
plot she wasn't stupid she recognized
that this was
the plans for a crime so she called the
Manila police the Manila police came and
said oo this looks big they called the
Philippine intelligence service they
went to the
apartment and said uhoh we better call
the
Americans and then the Americans came
and you know took the
information it's being plotted by this
person MTAR MTAR realized Iz he had been
blown so he just disappeared it was
months after the capture of Abu
zua that Abu zua told FBI agent Ali
safan during an interrogation that MTAR
he actually laughed when he said it he
said you don't know who MTAR is and Ali
said no we know the name MTAR but we
don't know who that is and he laughed
and he said I'll give you the name it's
khed muham
Med we had never heard of this person
before but then when we started to
investigate we realized oh my God he
went to school in North
Carolina and he's smart and he has
access to
money and then we realized what we were
up against it took us another year to
find him and to capture him we found him
in a safe house in R pindy
Pakistan and we've had him ever since
you had him in guantan Bay where there
there are over 700 people that have been
held and almost almost no convictions
we'll get to that in a second um tell me
about the operation it's an
extraordinary operation that you were
that you were in charge of that you
engineered essentially designed to
capture
zua um and you got him um and he was
yeah you tell the story what how did how
did that happen John right so we got
uh we received notice from a sister
agency that abua was exact words
somewhere in
Pakistan Pakistan has 250 million people
and they said well he's moving back and
forth between lore and faisalabad well
lore has 12 million people and fisat has
7 million
people so what do you mean go catch him
but go catch him how the country is the
size of Texas and there's no technology
like we have today I mean
there's are they even using mobile
phones cell phones at that stage barely
yeah they're all they're all just flip
phones and that's when you could go into
any kiosk and buy a phone make one call
and throw it in the trash so um all we
knew is that he was just going back and
forth and back and forth and back and
forth between FIS labad and
lore so we tried several different
things I won't bore you with the
failures but we just couldn't couldn't
get it any closer
and you know it's funny once we finally
caught him we also retrieved his diary
and he knew we were on his tail
sometimes we were three days behind
sometimes one time we were an hour
behind where there was still food on the
table and it was still
warm so we were close but never quite
close enough finally I I sent a cable to
headquarters and I said I I just can't
think of any more ideas to catch him I
just can't think of anything can you
send this friend of mine to Pakistan he
was a a targeting analyst now analysts
are very different from targeting
analysts analysts sit and think the big
thoughts and write papers that they're
for the president but nobody really
reads them for the most part you know
what's going to happen five years from
now in you know
Taiwan or in the egyp economy nobody mro
geopolitics Big Ideas Big Ideas you know
somebody at the state Department's going
to read them and say oh that's
interesting or whatever targeting
analysts pour through literally millions
of pieces of data to try to geolocate
somebody so that we can either kill him
or capture him so this friend of mine
flew out from
headquarters and it wasn't until he
landed that I was able to tell him why
he was required
there and I said this is big man this is
going to make or break our careers we've
got to catch this guy and he said okay
I'll get started he took a piece of
Butcher Block paper about the size of a
small American billboard a roadside
advertisement and he wrote Abu zubeda in
the center put a circle around it and
then around that he wrote down all of
the
all of the phone numbers the email
addresses that had been in touch with
Abu Zeda or the the physical addresses
of people or places that had been in
touch with abuaba and then he did a
secondary and then a tertiary ring and
made connections between all these
different assets I I've said before it
it was pretty to look at after he was
done it looked like a spiderweb or like
a work of art really
but he he finally came to me and he said
look I can't get it to fewer than 13
sites 13 possibilities he's moving
constantly I said well gez we've never
hit more than two sites before in a
night we would do our our our raids at
two o'clock in the morning with a team
made up of CIA FBI and isi officers and
and
sometimes a handful of local police
although the pakistanis never knew who
the targets were we we would just say
look you know take our word for it it's
a it's a bad
guy um because we we couldn't risk them
you know bragging about it in their
headquarters and then one of the long
beards hears it and then tips off the
bad guy and either they're waiting to
Ambush us or they've already
escaped
so I said well gez we're gonna have to
hit all 13 sites
simultaneously so I I wrote a cable to
headquarters I told them what I needed I
needed 30
people I needed millions of dollars in
cash I needed guns
ammunition um secure Communications
night vision goggles stun grenades you
name it they
chartered aing
7337 loaded everything on it landed at
lore airport two days later we unloaded
everything I had purchased two safe
houses we put everything in the safe
houses
um and we briefed everybody so that they
knew see we couldn't tell anybody what
the operation was until they actually
arrived because we just couldn't
risk loose lips sinking the ship right
so I gathered
everybody CIA FBI isi and something
called the Punjab Elite Force it was a
SWAT team special weapons and tactics
counterterrorism team
that belonged to the state of Punjab in
central Pakistan and I I stood on the I
stood on a coffee table with everybody
gathered around me and I said at the
risk of sounding
melodramatic we're gonna have to
synchronize our watches like in the
movies and we did
check and I said here's the
plan those of you going to FIS labad we
had to Charter a bus there were so many
of us those of you going to if I leat
are going to get get on the bus at 10:30
this was at 10
p.m. um and you're going to go to the
safe house everybody else is going to
remain here at this safe
house at
01:30 you're going to make sure you have
all your weapons all your ammunition and
your secure
Communications which were encrypted
walkie-talkies um by
0140 leave the safe house house
0155 be at the Target 0158 make sure you
have clear line of sight with the Target
and exactly as the clock strikes two
break down the door separate the women
and children from the men grab all the
men and take them into custody then the
FBI comes in and takes thousands of
pictures of
everything and then we take it from
there
now earlier in the
day a colleague of mine and I went with
three
pakistanis to look at all 13 sites
because we wanted to make sure we
weren't being set up there was going to
be a gunfight it was going to be an IED
on the side of the road it was a setup
we wanted to make sure that we had
Ingress and egress it was all going to
be
safe one of the
sites was a py phone at a shishkabob
stand so clearly there's Al-Qaeda living
in the Neighborhood Senior enough to be
on the phone with Abu zubeda but you
can't raid a closed shishkabob stand at
two o'clock in the morning so we cut
that from the list that took us down to
12 while we were driving around most
most of the other places were mud Huts
corrugated tin roofs just Hobs
but while we were driving
around
um the analyst called me from Islam Abad
and he said listen I just got a call
from a friendly Western intelligence
service and they said that they had a
walk-in come in today a walk-in is
somebody who literally just walks in off
the street and saysi have intelligence
that I want to give to your intelligence
service
99% of the time they're either
lunatics they are what are called
intelligence pedlers they're going to
take $100 from you then they're going to
go to the British Embassy then the
French Embassy then the Israeli Embassy
and that's how they make a living or
their probes their hostile intelligence
Services just looking to see are your
doors armored are your windows you know
bomb resistant how many of your people
have guns where are the security cameras
so if they decide to attack your Embassy
they know where the vulnerabilities are
99% fall into those three categories 1%
are the real
deal so I said well he said that the
walkin says that there is a huge group
of al-Qaeda fighters in a big yellow
house and I
said I want to talk to the walk-in and
he said I already asked they said it's
impossible
and he can't be reconed which told me
that there was no walk-in that it was it
was an intercept that they didn't want
to tell us about they believed that the
information was important enough to pass
to the Americans but they didn't want us
to know that they had a tap on
somebody's phone that's fine we didn't
care so the analyst calls me again about
two hours later
well first of all we're driving through
the campus of the University of feisel
laad and when we came out the back gate
of
it we came to the to the Target site and
it was an enormous yellow
house and I said I said that's that's
the site that's the site that the
walk-in told us
about and the Pakistani lison officer
said I can tell you there's something
bad is going on in that house I said how
do you figure he said said it's 105°
today and all of the shutters are closed
they have to be broiling in there they
just must not want anybody to know that
that they're in there and I said we we
have to put a especially an especially
big team on that house we ended up
catching now I can't say I'm not allowed
to say exactly how many we caught dozens
of people inside that house then he
calls me the analyst calls me a second
time and he said zua just made a
terrible
mistake he
downloaded
his um his Hotmail emails from a
landline he accessed his Hotmail emails
with a
landline and I said oh my God I I knew
he would make a mistake this is what we
had been waiting for for
months and I said give me the
address so he gives me the address and
it corresponds to the final Target site
and I I I remember I have chills all
these years just thinking about it
telling the story I turned to my
colleague and I said we got him so we
drive to the address and it's an empty
field it's just an empty undeveloped
field I said how could this possibly be
we're sure that the call came from this
location and the Pakistani major kind of
laughed and he said no no he said this
is quite common in
Pakistan he said when a plot of land is
legally
divided the phone company assigns it a
telephone line even if there's nothing
built there so when something eventually
is built there you just turn the line on
but what happens is people will climb
the telephone pole they'll splice their
own telephone line into the the uh empty
lots telephone line so they can make
calls and the bill goes to the owner of
the vacant
lot and I said so so he's here
somewhere how do we figure out what
house is stealing the
line he calls a tech officer a young
Pakistani technical officer the kid
looked like he was 18 years old he
climbs the telephone pole goes through
this Medusa's head of wires he literally
follows it fist over fist down the
telephone pole down the Alley we're
following him and he says it's that
house right
there and that's where we got
him so the all of those operations took
place at exact had to take place at
exactly the same time was it was it
about one o'clock in the morning I think
or two o'clock in the morning yeah two
o'clock in the
morning I I I remember going to the roof
of the safe house I looked at my watch
and I said 0200 here we go M and as soon
as I said it we could hear this sound in
the distance the sound of metal on metal
like boink boink boink and I said that's
not
good that's gun this colleague of mine
and I and then we heard gunshots and I
said oh that's really not good so I got
on the walkie-talkie and I knew which
site was the closest and I said site 13
what's going on over there and he shouts
shots fired shots fired they're firing
back at us
and I was like oh my God we jumped into
the car we sped over there as quickly as
we could and it was a scene of
chaos there was one
man just laying dead in the street like
obviously dead his eyes were
open there was another man who looked
like he was dead or he was almost dead
and then there was a third who was just
screaming bloody murder with a gunshot
wound straight through the center of his
femur and I shouted at the pakistanis I
said' damn it I said take them alive our
orders were to take them alive but this
stupid Pakistani policeman with an AK-47
just started shooting them as they're
jumping from the roof of the safe house
to the roof of the neighboring house to
escape the dead man was a Syrian bomb
maker the second person
shot may or may not have been abua we
didn't know at that point the third was
Abu zaba's bodyguard also Syrian
so
so I said who who is this guy the
Pakistani said to me we got him we got
your man I said which one is he this one
was the one who was almost dead I said
that that doesn't look anything like AB
AA we had this we had this like
six-year-old passport photo of a very
handsome young man with a close closely
cropped beard and
mustache um this guy was fat clean
shaven crazy hair going all over the
place I said that that doesn't look
anything like
abua
so my my colleague said what do you want
to do I said I don't know what the [__]
to do so I I called the analyst I said
look we may have gotten him but I I
don't know if this is the guy and he
said get me a shot of his of his um his
eye I'll run a retinal
scan so I kneel down over him and I
shouted um ifun open your
eyes nothing so I pulled I pulled his
eyelids up but his eyes were rolled back
in his head and I said I said look he's
he's dying he's bleeding to death I
can't I can't get a shot of his eyes he
was shot in the thigh the groin in the
stomach with this
AK-47 so he said get me a picture of his
ear and I didn't know until that night
that no two people on earth have the
same ears they're like fingerprints so I
took a picture of his ear remember 2002
phones didn't have cameras so I took a
picture of his ear I plugged my phone
into the camera and I was able to
transmit the picture through the phone
back to the analyst he sent the picture
to headquarters they ran the ear scan
and then they said it's him headquarters
in the United States yeah so this took
some time you might imagine it took 15
20 minutes in the meantime we're trying
to stanch the the bleeding and it was
just nightmarish they came back they
said it's him we picked him up we threw
him in the back of this filthy Toyota
pickup truck that we just commandeered
from some poor guy happen to be driving
through the neighborhood in the middle
of the night and we drove him to filabot
hospital which was a rough place the
story is too long to really get into the
details but they tried as best they
could to try to get the bleeding to stop
he was I mean just as fast as they could
pump the blood into him it was just
leaking right out of him uh but Al-Qaeda
got word that we had gotten it and they
started driving by the hospital and just
opening fire on the hospital so I said
to the Pakistani major if they realize
how lightly armed we are we're we're
dead can you get a helicopter in here
and he said yeah I think so so he makes
a call about 20 minutes later this
helicopter lands in the park parking lot
I just walked right into the operating
room I put my shirt up and I said doc
wrap it up we have to go they sewed him
closed as quickly as they could we put
him on the helicopter we flew him to a
Pakistani military base about 50 miles
away they rushed him into surgery there
and then at one point the doctor came
out and he said
look I've never seen wounds this severe
where the patient lived you should tell
your people to be prepared for his death
so I called the analyst I said you
should tell headquarters they don't
think he's going to live the
night and then he did and I sat with him
for the next 56
hours 56 hours um I've never been so
tired in my life um so you keep this guy
alive you mean you know this you know
who this guy is at this stage there
supposed to be one of the most events of
your life you know how big this is not
just for your career but for for the
United States I knew it was lifechanging
yeah it was lifechanging and for the
United States I mean you
know the analyst told me that when the
station chief called Headquarters he
called the director of the CIA directly
and the entire CIA leadership was in the
in the room and George Tennant the CIA
director said they got it him and the
whole place erupted into cheers and then
he immediately called the
president so I mean people were I mean
everybody
in you know the intelligence community
in in Washington was waiting for the
call so you got we got Abu zubeda um
rendition happens now right so we're
we're taking him back to Guantanamo or
he went to Guantanamo in I think it was
2004 but for two years he was moved from
Secret prison to secret prison all
around the world subjected to merciless
torture and um and by CIA oper
operatives by CIA you know it's even
worse than that by CIA contractors right
yeah Contra be local kind of Syrian or
Sudanese or any these were two
sociopathic American
psychologists by the name uh names of um
James Mitchell and Bruce jessen who had
pitched to the CIA director a torture
program that they called enhanced
interrogation techniques um they also
described it as learned
helplessness that you utterly break him
psychologically and then he'll tell you
everything you want to know the problem
is that torture simply doesn't work
besides the fact that it's immoral
unethical and illegal it doesn't work
they will tell you anything that they
think you want to hear just to get you
to stop torturing them and then you have
to assign a team of analysts to take the
next six months to go through this
information to figure out what was
nonsense and what was actionable and the
stuff that's actionable by the time you
get to it is so old that it's not
actionable anymore
you know especially when it comes to
counterterrorism time is of the essence
and you have to move on it quickly
otherwise once it gets stale either the
operation has taken place or it's been
moved or it's been cancelled or the
target has just scattered to the wind so
there there was no we knew in 2001 2002
2003 that there was no utility
whatsoever in torture and techniques so
the only thing that would explain it is
some kind of sadism
yes you know people underestimate the
motivation of Revenge after 911 3,000
Americans were killed on one day because
we were asleep at the
switch and so you know this this was
that one opportunity this is how it was
viewed at the senior levels this one
opportunity to redeem ourselves right to
not just disrupt the next attack but to
kill or capture the entire Al-Qaeda
leadership and you know as as you said
you look into the abyss and the abyss is
looking right back at you yeah you know
I I say all the time too and I mean this
very very
seriously the CIA leaders who conceived
of the torture
program implemented the torture program
defended the torture
program continue to support the torture
program even knowing deep down that it
didn't work because when they
die their obituaries are going to say
that they were the creators and the
leaders and the implementers of torture
and if they keep repeating the LIE over
and over and over again that it helped
keep Americans
safe then that's a way to try to ensure
their own legacy I'm here to tell you
that they're lying to us it wasn't
effective it wasn't helpful and if
anything it made anti-American terrorism
worse in 2007 you went on ABC um a few
years later you left the CIA shortly
afterwards in around 2004 205 and you
priv private
Enterprise something happens 2007
arrives you do a an interview with ABC
with Brian Ross is it where you decide
now you must have been your wife was
also in the C CIA at this stage you must
have had this multiple conversations
with your wife this is what I'm going to
do and you must both together must have
known that oh my god when when you do
this because you you draw a direct line
between torture and the United States
President yes I did in fact the
president said the next day his exact
words I don't know this man I don't know
this man's motivation I don't know why
this man threw me under the
bus the truth is he had been lying to
the American people you know I I did not
initially accept Brian Ross's
invitation um but what happened that
week was uh there was a press conference
a presidential press conference and
there had been reports from the uh
International Committee of the Red Cross
Human Rights Watch and Amnesty
International all saying that the CIA
was torturing its prisoners and so a
reporter asked President Bush about
these reports and he looked right in the
camera and he said we do not
torture and I remember telling my wife
we were sitting there on the couch
watching this and I said he is a
bald-faced
liar he is looking the American people
in the eye and he's lying to
them but you know that's
Washington four days later it was a
Friday and he was walking from the south
Portico of the White House to the
helicopter to fly to Camp d David for
the weekend and a reporter shouted a
question about torture and he paused and
he turned and said well if there is
torture it's because of a rogue CIA
officer and I said to my wife they're G
to try to pin this on me so I called
Brian Ross and I said I'll do your
interview and I decided that no matter
what he asked me I was going to tell the
truth so what I ended up saying was the
CIA was torturing its prisoners that t
was official US government policy and
the policy had been personally approved
by the
president and then and the entire weight
of the US government fell on my head
yeah when you're in those crosshairs um
they say the process is the punishment
so they're goingon to bankrupt you
financially so it's gonna they did yeah
you know the irony though the irony is
that the bush justice department uh
investigated me for a full year from
December of 2007 to December of 2008 and
then they determined that I had not
committed a crime they sent a
declination letter to my attorney saying
that um I had not revealed classified
information
because torture is a crime and it is
illegal to classify a criminal
act so I was off scott free my wife and
I were so excited we actually went to
dinner that night to celebrate four
weeks later Barack Obama became
president and John Brennan who was one
of the fathers one of the founders of
the torture program uh became Obama's
Chief um uh intelligence adviser he
became the deputy National Security
adviser for counterterrorism and then he
went on to be the CIA director John and
I never liked each other and he and I
were on completely opposite sides of
this torture issue I had no idea that as
soon as he entered the White House John
asked the justice department to secretly
reopen the case against me and so for
the next three years my phones were
tapped my emails were being intercepted
and teams of FBI agents were following
me everywhere I went and then finally in
January of
2012 this is more than four years after
I blew the whistle I was arrested and
charged with three counts of Espionage
one count of violating the intelligence
identities protection act of 1981 a very
obscure law and making a false
statement we were never really sure what
the false statement was supposed to have
been um but what they did as you just
alluded to is they waited until I went
bankrupt and then they dropped the
Espionage charges now remember too
Espionage can be a death penalty
charge um they were offering me 45 years
in prison if I would plead guilty I said
I'm not going to do 45 minutes in prison
I said you guys are the criminals here
not
me and you know you're right the process
is the punishment it it wrecked
everything I socially my my friends my
former colleagues even family members
walked away your wife was still in the
CIA at this stage was she or had she
left yes sir she was fired on the day of
my arrest only because she was married
to
me yes there's no HR process here you're
out the door out the CIA is an usual
organization in that out of the entire
US Government CIA officers serve at the
pleasure of the
president um we don't get the same Civil
Service protections that everybody else
in government gets if the president
doesn't like your face you're out and
there's nothing you can do and the
president didn't like me
well John Brandon didn't like you either
um it seems I mean the the the fact that
they were torturing people like they
said if they can pin it on a rogue um
then they don't have to take Collective
account I I that's right I had a friend
in the CIA who we go to the same church
we're in the same men's group he just
happens to be a brigadier general in the
Army and a psychiatrist at the CIA and
he said to me one day you know they call
you the human rights guy behind your
back and I said I know I've heard them
he said you know that's not a compliment
right and I said Steve I'm on the right
side of history and they are
not people might people watching and
watching your story might say the only
the impetus to act was when you realize
it wasn't necessarily moral or
ideological stand you were taking even
though clearly you were very
uncomfortable with the whole torture
thing it was when you realized you were
in the crossair yes that that's when you
jumped and moved um because you knew you
were in big trouble
here and I wanted to save myself um
still you know I kept waiting for
somebody to say something because after
the absera capture I I got a big
promotion I became the deputy I became
the deputy director's executive
assistant and so in that job I got to
see literally everything that the CIA
was doing around the world
well there were dozens of cables coming
back from the secret site saying this is
illegal I'm resigning or I'm curtailing
my assignment I'm coming back to
headquarters I can't believe we're
torturing this man this is this is
unethical this violates my hypocritic
oath so I wasn't the only person who
thought this was a criminal act and I
thought surely somebody is going to say
something and then nobody said anything
so in the interim I I had done research
I'm not an attorney so I started
researching the law and the law was
crystal clear that this whole program
was illegal I felt confident that I was
on the right side of
this you the process was the punishment
in your case I remember you you did
mention the fact that at one point you
thought you were sitting inside your
wife watching television at one point
you thought about going into the garage
putting the key in the ignition oh yeah
and saying okay guys I'm out of here
yeah I did um so it must have been
torturous reputationally you know they
say um one of the one will story in his
book the status game has highlighted
that one of the the what makes people
take their own lives men in particular
is a sudden un catastrophic loss of
status right so as well as all of this
happening you have this massive
catastrophic
reputational GL Global your your your
your community see you as a
traitor potentially you have the the the
American justice system all over you
you're paying $750 an hour to to lawyers
that you can't how can anybody afford
that and there were 11 of
them and yeah do you I still owe them I
still owe them
$1,150,000 that they will never see
never so were they were they were they
doing this work pro bono John or what
was the how did you of of the 11 six
were pro bono um the remaining five um I
still owe $1.15
million um but with that
said they told me early on look this
case is far bigger than John kiraku this
is a a case that involves constitutional
protections it's a case that involves
the rule of law it's a case that
involves the war on whistleblowers you
know between 1917 and and 2009 three
Americans were charged with Espionage
for speaking to the Press just under
John Brennan and Barack Obama nine of us
were charged with Espionage for speaking
to the Press that's more that's that's
three times all previous presidents
combined so there's a real transparency
problem in government why do you why do
you think the Obama Administration was
so
determined as opposed to the bush ad
surely the Bush Administration would
want to to get you you'd think as crazy
as it sounds the Bush Administration was
more concerned about the rule of law um
and I'm telling you this as a third
generation Democrat I'm no longer a
Democrat I'm independent independent um
I I hate everybody equally and um but
what it was was that there was two
factors John Brennan had an obsession
with National Security leaks and number
two Barack Obama uh was so inexperienced
to be president that he just did on
National Security issues he just did
whatever Brennan told him to do guy was
a senator for two
years yeah yeah I was Intelligence
experience at all nothing yeah um so you
eventually you you you take the plea you
do the two years in jail you come out
what is your status now are you
considered a convicted can you get a can
you work like how does how does it
affect your your your ability your
powers of recovery how did you recover
from all of
this honestly I have to thank my my wife
now my ex-wife unfortunately the the the
pressure that this puts on families it's
it's insurmountable but she said look
she said you have to embrace this you
can't run from it or pretend it didn't
happen you have to embrace it you didn't
do anything wrong
you have to be the the torture
whistleblower whether you want to or
not and she was right you know I
couldn't get a job stocking shelves at a
grocery store working at Target working
at a gas station I applied for a job as
a baggage handler at the airport no one
would touch
me
so I decided to just make my own work I
started writing and I write
constantly now I I'm working on my ninth
book um my first made the New York Times
bestsellers list my second one two
literary awards including one of the big
four um I write a column for covert
Action magazine I read a column for a
Consortium news at the time I also had a
column at reader supported news I do
op-eds for the Los Angeles Times I
lecture at different universities
University of Southern California the
University of Salam Mona and Spain I'm
starting a global speaking tour in
Ireland in two weeks so I just made my
own path and little by little people
begin coming around to the point where
in 2016 I was nominated by a Swedish
parliamentarian for the Nobel Peace
Prize um I was invited by the commandant
of the uh Military Academy at West Point
to speak to the Freshman Class about
ethics and intelligence
operations um I've had three FBI agents
most recently two weeks ago three FBI
agents who were on my case um apologize
to me and say that it was a political
case and that they were forced to do it
and that they were sorry that they
hadn't spoken
out so you know I I'm comfortable with
who I am I don't know if the if the
torturers are but I know I am
um and you're coming to Ireland in two
week a couple of questions I wanted
would be remiss of me not to ask you um
Shannon Airport in the west of Ireland
there was rumors that it was used as a
staging post for rendition are you aware
of anything to do with shanon I heard
those same rumors um we didn't do it
while we didn't use Shannon while I was
there so I have no Insight information
but I can tell you that I also know
several very very good investigative
journalists who have taken years to go
through flight data that's publicly
available just very few people have the
wherewithal to put it together and they
are 100% confident that Shannon has been
used uh for rendition plates yes what's
your perspective on Edward Snowden
American hero or American oh I I think
Snowden is a Bonafide hero the American
people would never have known that the
American government in violation of the
law was spying on us
not only do we have a law in black and
white that the US government is not
permitted to spy on Americans it is a
part of nsa's Charter its founding
Charter that it may not spy on Americans
and now a majority of its work is spying
on Americans we wouldn't have had any
idea that that was the case had it not
been for Ed Snowden has Ed Snowden
changed anything no he's he's just
illuminated he's shine light into the
place that's SE yeah the the change
hasn't come and and specifically the
change that you're talking about is
called section 702 of the um foreign
intelligence surveillance act now every
two years when that section is
renewed permitting warrantless
wiretapping of American citizens there
are more votes against it in
Congress I'm confident that eventually
we're going to get to the
point where NSA won't be able to spy on
us anymore we're not there
yet but we'll get there wow that's a big
bold statement that would be a massive
um positive impact um it would and you
know the funny thing too is and I'll
preface this this by saying I disagree
with
95% of everything that Donald Trump
stands for but Donald Trump is right
about warrantless wiretapping and
section 702 and NSA spying on Americans
because NSA spied on him you know it was
the Clinton Administration that
authorized NSA to spy on Donald Trump
and the Trump campaign in 2016 and
that's just not
right that's shocking yeah um that has
been well documented and it's
indisputable right or was there a court
case around that or yeah and and the
justice department said no we didn't spy
on him it's that there were some people
around him that we thought maybe were
doing illegal thing no no if you suspect
the man of a crime and panel a grand
jury and investigate the crime you don't
go to a secret office in the justice
department and say we want you to tap
Donald Trump's phones don't tell anybody
yeah that's you can't do that that's not
the American
way last question um I think I know what
you'll say but if you could change
anything if you could go back and
looking back at your life
um would you do the Brian Ross interview
again yes
but and this is something I tell every
wouldbe whistleblower who asks me for
advice hire a lawyer
first before you speak a single word
hire a lawyer skilled in National
Security Law and make sure he is sitting
next to you when you do the
interview I had to be reactive which was
a terrible terrible
mistake other whistleblowers should be
proactive John kiraku thank you so much
it's been a a pleasure and fascinating
to meet you your story is extraordinary
and um I wish you every success in
rebuilding and recovering thanks so much
and posterity let
how it it will be how you will be
remembered for your services to the
United States and and for for revealing
um a shocking episode in its history
thank you so much may I make one plug
I'm excited to begin a speaking to her
it's going to be uh a 100 event Global
speaking tour but we're starting in
Ireland in two weeks and then moving on
to 40 dates in uh in England Scotland
and Wales um if you go to Tigers Lane
Studios which is a London based
production company uh the schedule is
there there's still some tickets
available and I would love to see
everybody yeah I'm going to put a link
to I check the tickets are tickets are
available it's in the Crown Plaza in
North Dublin and you're you're going to
be in Belfast as well I'll put a link to
it in the description box there are
still some tickets available that can be
grabbed and uh I think everybody yeah
should should go and meet and see it
would be a lot of fun thanks so much
pleas great to meet you love you to meet
you too thank you John
[Music]